A Guide to the Rockefeller Foundation records, officers' diaries, RG 12, M-R FA393
Rockefeller Archive Center
- Marshall, John
  - Trip to Europe, 5 October 1958 - 5 November 1958; Marshall, John; Rockefeller Foundation. Division of Humanities.; 70 pages (Box 304, Reel M Mar 12, Frame 213)
    The diary is arranged by interview and visit. John Marshall is an associate director of the Rockefeller Foundation's Humanities Division. The program is concerned with history, philosophy, linguistics and the arts. Grants are organized into intercultural studies, humanistic research, the arts and special projects. Marshall takes a trip to Turkey and Germany. During his time in Turkey, he documents the Robert College's special grant for establishing general and higher education curriculum in Turkey, the Istanbul Conservatory, Institute of Economic History and projects on Koran readings. During his ten days in Germany he details his general observations.
    Germany; Humanities; Education; Music; Turkey; Arts; Diaries
  - 28 October 1958 - 20 February 1959, Marshall, John; Rockefeller Foundation. Division of Humanities.; 163 pages (Box 304, Reel M Mar 12, Frame 283)
    The diary is arranged by interview and visit. John Marshall is an associate director of the Rockefeller Foundation's Humanities Division. The program is concerned with history, philosophy, linguistics and the arts. Grants are organized into intercultural studies, humanistic research, the arts and special projects. Marshall takes a trip to Europe from 28 October- 16 December 1958. During this time he visits the Hague and attends the Unesco general conference. Includes List of Diaries Inadvertantly Destroyed, 1 January-20 Febrary 1959.
    England; Netherlands; Switzerland; France; Humanities; Diaries
  - Index, January 1959 - August 1959; Rockefeller Foundation; Marshall, John
    January to August 1959
  - Trip to Europe, October 28-December 16, 1958; Rockefeller Foundation. Division of Humanities.; Marshall, John (Box 304, Reel M Mar 12, Frame 284)
    The diary is arranged by interview and visit. John Marshall is an associate director of the Rockefeller Foundation's Humanities Division. The program is concerned with history, philosophy, linguistics and the arts. Grants are organized into intercultural studies, humanistic research, the arts and special projects. Marshall takes a trip to Europe from 28 October- 16 December 1958. During this time he visits the Hague and attends the Unesco general conference.
  - List of Diaries Inadvertently Destroyed, 1959-1960; Rockefeller Foundation. Division of Humanities.; Marshall, John (Box 304, Reel M Mar 12, Frame 443)
    1 January-20 Febrary 1959.
  - 1959 February 20-June 19, Rockefeller Foundation. Division of Humanities.; Marshall, John; 105 pages (Box 304, Reel M Mar 12, Frame 451)
    The diary is arranged by interview and visit. John Marshall is an associate director of the Rockefeller Foundation's Humanities Division. The program is concerned with history, philosophy, linguistics and the arts. Grants are organized into intercultural studies, humanistic research, the arts and special projects. Marshall tours Italy, France and England for opportunities and interests in humanities programs abroad.
    Theater; Music; Linguistics; Language and languages; Diaries; United States; Drama; Humanities; Arts
  - Trip to Europe, May 11-June 19, 1959; Rockefeller Foundation. Division of Humanities.; Marshall, John (Box 304, Reel M Mar 12, Frame 556)
    Humanities; France; England; Italy
  - 1959 June 23-August 19, Rockefeller Foundation. Division of Humanities.; Marshall, John (Reel M Mar 12, Frame 626, Box 304)
    The diary is arranged by interview and visit. John Marshall is an associate director of the Rockefeller Foundation's Humanities Division. The program is concerned with history, philosophy, linguistics and the arts. Grants are organized into intercultural studies, humanistic research, the arts and special projects. Marshall attends the Harvard International Seminar from 21-24 July 1959.
    Humanities; Drama; Arts; United States; Theater
  - Index - European Trip, 1959; Rockefeller Foundation. Division of Humanities.; Marshall, John (Box 304, Reel M Mar 12, Frame 692)
    Bellagio, United States, and Rhineland Valley.
    70 pages
  - Trip to Rhineland, 1960; Rockefeller Foundation. Division of Humanities.; Marshall, John; 116 pages (Box 304, Reel M Mar 12, Frame 693)
    The diary is arranged by interview and visit. John Marshall is an associate director of the Rockefeller Foundation's Humanities Division. The program is concerned with history, philosophy, linguistics and the arts. Grants are organized into intercultural studies, humanistic research, the arts and special projects. Marshall visits Germany, Austria and Italy. He surveys Rockefeller Foundation interests in German humanities programs and assesses higher education institutions. In Italy at the Villa Serbelloni, he details the European Association of American Studies Conference on Research on the American Image in Europe. The diary also includes summaries of his trips to the Rhineland that focuses on history of the region.
    Diaries; Education; Germany; History; Humanities; Italy; Literature; Philosophy and religion; United States; Austria
- Mason, Max
  Charles Max Mason (commonly known as Max Mason) was born in 1877 in Madison, Wisconsin. A well-regarded mathematician, Mason's eclectic career spanned the fields of teaching, research, university administration and philanthropy.
  Mason graduated from the University of Wisconsin-Madison in 1898 before earning his Ph.D. in mathematics from the University of Göttingen in Germany in 1903. Upon his return to the U.S., Mason taught mathematics at both the Massachusetts Institute of Technology and Yale University before becoming a professor of physics at the University of Wisconsin-Madison in 1908.
  During World War I Mason took a leave of absence in order to work on the Submarine Committee of the National Research Council (NRC). This work was instrumental in the development of the Mason Hydrophone, a detection device that allowed naval crews to pinpoint the location of German submarines. This research later contributed to the development of sonar detectors in World War II. Following the war, Mason resumed his career at the University of Wisconsin-Madison.
  In 1925 Mason was asked to become president of the University of Chicago. He accepted the position but remained there for only three years before becoming the director of the Natural Sciences Division of the Rockefeller Foundation (RF). Mason was quickly promoted, and in 1929 he was named president of the Foundation. At the Foundation Mason's personal interest in behavioral research influenced both the experimental biology program of the Natural Sciences Division and the Medical Sciences Division, where initiatives in psychiatry flourished under his supervision.
  In 1936 Mason resigned from the RF and joined the team overseeing the construction of the RF-funded Palomar Observatory in California. This project, completed in 1948, allowed Mason to return to physics. Throughout his life he published a number of articles and books in the fields of mathematics and physics, including The Electromagnetic Field (1929), which he co-authored with fellow RF staffer Warren Weaver. Mason was also elected a member of the National Academy of Sciences and the German Mathematical Society.
  Following the completion of the observatory, Mason retired to Claremont, California. Max Mason passed away in 1961.
  - Index, 1928-1929; Rockefeller Archive Center; Mason, Max; 4 pages; Pages 118, 140, and 178 are missing. Pages 216 and 217 do not exist. (Box 305, Reel M Mas 1, Frame 1)
    Description
    Officers of the Rockefeller Foundation in New York and its staff members in the field often visited educational, scientific and research institutions and laboratories in many parts of the world to maintain contacts and assess work being done. Officers and field staff frequently conferred with government officials regarding the operation of the RF's programs. In order to preserve accurate records for the guidance of other RF officers, those who carried on these activities kept diaries of their day-to-day contacts and impressions. These diaries were sent to the RF office, where they circulated among officers and staff to the extent deemed advisable. Diaries are of two types: regular daily diaries, and special trip diaries. Some diaries have indexes, which are bound in the annual volume; indexing was not a requirement but was left to the discretion of the officers, and not all diaries are indexed.
    Copies
    A 35mm microfilm access copy is available for researchers. A digitized version of the microfilm is also available in the RAC Digital Archive.
    indexes (reference sources); Woods Hole (Mass.); Rockefeller Foundation
  - 1928 October 5-1929 December 30, Mason, Max; Rockefeller Foundation; 3 pages; 114 pages (Box 305, Reel M Mas 1, Frame 5)
    This diary records Mr. Mason's interviews and meetings with researchers across the United States, meetings with Rockefeller Foundation fellows and native administrators from Chinese universities, and memoranda of internal discussions among staff on Rockefeller Foundation natural science research projects around the globe.
    Diaries; China; United States
  - Index, 1930; Mason, Max (Reel M Mas 1, Frame 167, Box 305)
    Index of diary for 1930; 4 pages. Includes a list of trips taken around United States and a trip to Europe during summer months (5/9/30-8/28/30).
  - 1930, Rockefeller Foundation; Mason, Max; 149 pages (Box 305, Reel M Mas 1, Frame 171)
    This diary records Mr. Mason's interviews and travels between January 2 and December 30 1930. The diary shows that he met with and interviewed natural science researchers and university administrators both in the United States and Europe, and coordinated with the Rockefeller Foundation's senior staff to ensure funding of projects to a maximum number of candidates at the earliest part of the Great Depression in the United States. While the depression is never directly referenced, the diary contains a copy of the "New Mexico Tax Bulletin" of 1930, a 23-page report which provided figures, estimates, and conclusions on the size and scope of the state's bonded debt in 1930. On a separate note, more than half the diary appears to be handwritten notes penned (almost illegibly) by Mason spanning several weeks and topics.
    United States; Europe; Diaries
  - Index, 1931; Mason, Max (Box 305, Reel M Mas 1, Frame 387)
    Index of diary for 1931; 4 pages. Includes a list of travel dates and locations from February to November of 1931.
  - 1931, Mason, Max; 70 pages (Reel M Mas 1, Frame 391, Box 305)
    This diary records Mr. Mason's interviews and travels between January 2 and December 30 1931, specifically with researchers across the United States, meetings with Rockefeller Foundation fellows and university administrators, and memoranda of internal discussions among staff on Rockefeller Foundation natural science research projects around the globe.
    United States; Diaries
  - Index, 1932-1933; Mason, Max (Reel M Mas 1, Frame 480, Box 305)
    Index of diary for 1932-1933; 4 pages. Includes a list of travel dates and locations from February 8, 1932 through December 20, 1933, including travel to Europe.
  - 1932-1933, Mason, Max; 84 pages (Reel M Mas 1, Frame 487, Box 305)
    This diary records Mr. Mason's interviews and travels between January 2, 1932 and December 29, 1933, specifically with researchers across the United States, meetings with Rockefeller Foundation fellows and university administrators, and memoranda of internal discussions among staff on Rockefeller Foundation natural science research projects around the globe. Further, Mason also traveled to Europe for a brief period of time to meet with key staff of the Paris office, including important fellows and field directors. A number of discussions recorded in the diary are concerned with the difficulties surrounding funding and maintaining research projects throughout the United States and Europe despite the depressed economic conditions.
    Diaries; Europe; United States
  - Index, 1934-1936; Mason, Max (Reel M Mas 1, Frame 609, Box 305)
    Index of diary for 1934-1936; 4 pages. Includes a list of travel dates and locations within the United States during that time period.
  - 1934-1936, Mason, Max; 74 pages (Reel M Mas 1, Frame 613, Box 305)
    This diary records Mr. Mason's travel and interviews with researchers across the United States, meetings with Rockefeller Foundation fellows and university administrators, and memoranda of internal discussions among staff on Rockefeller Foundation natural science research projects around the globe between January 2, 1934 and June, 1936. A number of discussions recorded in the diary are concerned with the difficulties surrounding funding and maintaining research projects throughout the United States and Europe despite the depressed economic conditions.
- May, Stacy
  - 1934-1937 (Box 306)
  - 1938-1940 (Box 306)
- McCoy, Oliver Rufus
  - 1946-1949 (Box 306)
  - 1950-1951 (Box 306)
  - 1952-1955 (Box 307)
- McIntosh, William A.
  - 1931 (Box 307)
  - 1932 (Box 308)
  - 1933 (Box 308)
  - 1934 (Box 308)
  - 1935 (Box 309)
  - 1936 (Box 309)
  - 1937 (Box 309)
  - 1938 (Box 310)
  - 1939 (Box 310)
  - 1940 (Box 310)
  - 1941 (Box 311)
  - 1942 (Box 311)
  - 1943 (Box 311)
  - 1944 (Box 312)
  - 1945 (Box 312)
  - 1946 (Box 313)
  - 1947 (Box 313)
  - 1948 (Box 314)
  - 1949 (Box 314)
  - 1950-1951 (Box 314)
  - 1952 (Box 315)
  - 1953 (Box 315)
  - 1954-1955 (Box 315)
- McKelvey, John J., Jr.
  - 1952 (Box 315)
  - 1953 (Box 316)
  - 1954 (Box 316)
  - 1955 (Box 316)
  - 1956 (Box 317)
  - 1957 (Box 317)
  - 1958 (Box 317)
  - 1959 (Box 318)
  - 1960 (Box 318)
  - 1961 (Box 319)
  - 1962 (Box 319)
  - 1963 (Box 320)
  - 1964 (Box 320)
  - 1965 (Box 320)
  - 1966 (Box 321)
  - 1967 (Box 321)
  - 1970-1977 (Box 321)
  - 1978-1983 (Box 322)
- McKinley, Erskine W.
  - 1956 (Box 322)
  - 1957 January-August (Box 322)
  - 1957 September-December (Box 323)
  - 1958 January-September (Box 323)
  - 1958 October-December (Box 323)
  - 1959 January-June (Box 324)
  - 1959 July-December (Box 324)
  - 1960 (Box 324)
- Mercadante, Lucille T.
  - 1967-1968 (Box 325)
- Milam, Daniel F.
  - 1942-1943 (Box 325)
  - 1944 (Box 325)
  - 1945 (Box 326)
  - 1946 (Box 326)
  - 1947-1948 (Box 326)
- Miller, Harry M.
  - 1932, Rockefeller Foundation. Division of Natural Sciences; Miller, Harry M.; 144 pages (Reel M Mil 1, Frame 1, Box 327)
    Organized according to interview and visit, Miller discusses fellowship opportunities and grants with professionals in the field of natural science. As an Assistant Fellowship Administrator in Europe working from the RF Paris Office, he is involved in the selection of RF fellows. The goal of the Natural Sciences Division is to support fellowships in direct support of special fields of scientific interest. These opportunities would provide extensive training in the disciplines essential to effective research. In 1932, Miller tours and surveys various laboratories and research centers in England, Wales and Germany. The diary includes a table of contents, letters, memorandum and a travel log.
    Diaries; Zoology; Wales; Biology -- Research; Physiology; Germany; France; Chemistry, Organic; England
  - 1933 January 25-July 31, Rockefeller Foundation. Division of Natural Sciences; Miller, Harry M.; 163 pages (Reel M Mil 1, Frame 203, Box 327)
    Organized according to interview and visit, Miller discusses fellowship opportunities and grants with professionals in the field of natural science. As the Fellowship Administrator in Europe working from the RF Paris Office, he is involved in the selection of RF fellows. The goal of the Natural Sciences Division is to support fellowships in direct support of special fields of scientific interest. These opportunities would provide extensive training in the disciplines essential to effective research. In 1933, Miller tours and surveys various laboratories and research centers in Europe. The diary includes a table of contents, letters, memorandum and a travel log.
    Chemistry, Organic; Czechoslovakia; Denmark; England; Diaries; France; Germany; Netherlands; Norway; Physics; Zoology; Sweden; Ukraine; Poland; Scotland; Agriculture; Plant pathology; Botany; Biology -- Research
  - 1933 August 4-December 16, Miller, Harry M.; Rockefeller Foundation. Division of Natural Sciences; 207 pages (Box 327, Reel M Mil 1, Frame 396)
    Organized according to interview and visit, Miller discusses fellowship opportunities and grants with professionals in the field of natural science. As the Fellowship Administrator in Europe working from the RF Paris Office, he is involved in the selection of RF fellows. The goal of the Natural Sciences Division is to support fellowships in direct support of special fields of scientific interest. These opportunities would provide extensive training in the disciplines essential to effective research. In 1933, Miller tours and surveys various laboratories and research centers in Europe. The diary includes memorandum and a travel log.
    Agriculture; Biology -- Research; England; Botany; Chemistry; Germany; France; Italy; Hypophysectomy; Switzerland; Physics; Diaries; Zoology
  - 1934 January 12-June 25, Miller, Harry M.; Rockefeller Foundation. Division of Natural Sciences; 140 pages (Box 327, Reel M Mil 1, Frame 637)
    SCope and Contents note
    Organized according to interview and visit, Miller discusses fellowship opportunities and grants with professionals in the field of natural science. As the Assistant Director, he is involved in the selection of RF fellows. The goal of the Natural Sciences Division is to support fellowships in direct support of special fields of scientific interest. These opportunities would provide extensive training in the disciplines essential to effective research. In 1934, Miller tours and surveys various laboratories and research centers in Europe and the United States to visit fellows and become acquainted with specific research settings. The diary includes table of contents, memorandum and a travel log.
    England; Chemistry, Organic; Czechoslovakia; Netherlands; Physics; Germany; Hungary; Plant physiology; United States; Diaries; Botany; Biology -- Research; Austria; Zoology
  - 1934 June 27-December 7, Rockefeller Foundation. Division of Natural Sciences; Miller, Harry M.; 127 pages (Box 327, Reel M Mil 1, Frame 803)
    Organized according to interview and visit, Miller discusses fellowship opportunities and grants with professionals in the field of natural science. As the Assistant Director, he is involved in the selection of RF fellows. The goal of the Natural Sciences Division is to support fellowships in direct support of special fields of scientific interest. These opportunities would provide extensive training in the disciplines essential to effective research. In 1934, Miller tours and surveys various laboratories and research centers in Europe to visit fellows and become acquainted with specific research settings. The diary includes memorandum, "Supplement to Berlin-Munich Log" and a travel log.
    Diaries; Radiation; Psychology; Poland; Agriculture; Zoology; Veterinary medicine; Switzerland; Czechoslovakia; Chemistry, Organic; Chemistry; Biology -- Research; Germany; France; England; Plant pathology; Physics; Marine biology; Italy
  - 1935 January 14-June 25, Rockefeller Foundation. Division of Natural Sciences; Miller, Harry M.; 125 pages (Reel M Mil 1, Frame 956, Box 327)
    Organized according to interview and visit, Miller discusses fellowship opportunities and grants with professionals in the field of natural science. As the Assistant Director, he is involved in the selection of RF fellows. The goal of the Natural Sciences Division is to support fellowships in direct support of special fields of scientific interest. These opportunities would provide extensive training in the disciplines essential to effective research. In 1935, Miller tours and surveys various laboratories and research centers in Europe to visit fellows and become acquainted with specific research settings. The diary includes table of contents, memorandum, and a travel log.
    Physiology; Plant genetics; Poland; Russia; Diaries; England; Germany; Italy; Norway; Sweden; Botany; Biology -- Research; Denmark; Yugoslavia; Zoology
  - 1935 September 10-December 23, Rockefeller Foundation. Division of Natural Sciences; Miller, Harry M.; 192 pages (Reel M Mil 1, Frame 1,104, Box 327)
    Organized according to interview and visit, Miller discusses projects and research with professionals in the field of natural sciences. He is involved in the progress of Natural Science programs, selection of fellows, and development of new research. In 1935, Miller tours and surveys various laboratories and research centers in Europe and the United States to visit fellows and become acquainted with specific research settings. The diary includes an index, memorandum, and a travel log.
    Diaries; Biology -- Research; Blood; Zoology; Austria; Hematology; Germany; Physiology; Hungary; Czechoslovakia; Chemistry; England; United States; Switzerland
  - 1936 January 8-April 23, Rockefeller Foundation. Division of Natural Sciences; Miller, Harry M.; 132 pages (Box 328, Reel M Mil 2, Frame 1)
    Organized according to interview and visit, Miller discusses projects and research with professionals in the field of natural sciences. He is involved in the progress of Natural Science programs, selection of fellows, and development of new research. In 1936, Miller tours and surveys various laboratories and research centers in Europe to visit fellows and become acquainted with specific research settings. The diary includes a table of contents, memorandum, and a travel log.
    Germany; Hungary; France; Genetics; England; Botany; Chemistry, Organic; Pharmacology; Physiology; Ireland; Mathematics; Diaries; Biochemistry; Poland; Portugal; Romania; Spain; Switzerland; Yugoslavia; Zoology
  - 1936 May 1-December 16, Miller, Harry M.; Rockefeller Foundation. Division of Natural Sciences; 244 pages (Reel M Mil 2, Frame 150, Box 328)
    Organized according to interview and visit, Miller discusses projects and research with professionals in the field of natural sciences. He is involved in the progress of Natural Science programs, selection of fellows, and development of new research. In 1936, Miller surveys various laboratories, universities and research centers in Europe. Miller attends the 4th International Congress of Experimental Cytology. The diary includes a table of contents, memorandum, and a travel log. An outline report on "Meeting of Scientific Experts of the International Organization for Intellectual Cooperation" is also included.
    Turkey; Zoology; Croatia; Chemistry; Bulgaria; Botany; Biology -- Research; Pharmacology; Physiology; Serbia; Netherlands; Greece; Germany; France; England; Denmark; Cytology; Diaries
  - 1937 January 6-May 28, Miller, Harry M.; Rockefeller Foundation. Division of Natural Sciences; 142 pages (Reel M Mil 2, Frame 406, Box 328)
    Organized according to interview and visit, Miller discusses projects and research with professionals in the field of natural sciences. He is involved in the progress of Natural Science programs, selection of fellows, and development of new research. In 1937, Miller surveys various laboratories, universities and research centers in Europe.
    Scotland; Plant pathology; Physiology; Diaries; Norway; Italy; Histology; Zoology; Switzerland; England; Chemistry; Denmark; Bacteriology; Botany; Sweden; Anatomy; Karolinska Institutet